<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://donkeypoid.github.io</id>
    <title>类驴活动观察记录</title>
    <updated>2024-06-24T17:14:29.446Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://donkeypoid.github.io"/>
    <link rel="self" href="https://donkeypoid.github.io/atom.xml"/>
    <subtitle>A Donkey-in-Between</subtitle>
    <logo>https://donkeypoid.github.io/images/avatar.png</logo>
    <icon>https://donkeypoid.github.io/favicon.ico</icon>
    <rights>All rights reserved 2024, 类驴活动观察记录</rights>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Conventions in Game/Game Studies]]></title>
        <id>https://donkeypoid.github.io/post/RQQG8VR0I/</id>
        <link href="https://donkeypoid.github.io/post/RQQG8VR0I/">
        </link>
        <updated>2024-06-24T17:13:14.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Conventions in Game Studies</p>
]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Conventions in Game Studies</p>
<!-- more -->
<p><em>Bernard Perron</em><br>
Rules and Conventions</p>
<p>Roger Caillois, Man, Play, and Gam<br>
es :</p>
<p>“Any game is a system of rules. These define what is or not a game, that is, what is allowed and what is forbidden. These conventions are at the same time arbitrary, imperative, and without appeal. They cannot be violated on any account, or else the game ends right away and is destroyed by the same fact. ([1958] 1961, pp. 11–12, my translation)” (pdf)</p>
<p>“Conventions are then not seen as constitutive or operational rules. They are unwritten and/or implicit rules.” (pdf)</p>
<p>“On the contrary, conventions “cannot be broken; they can only be ignored or neglected”” (pdf)<br>
The Rules of Conventions</p>
<p>“In Peter J. Rabinowitz’s aforementioned theory of narrative, reading fiction is a conventional activity as it presupposes an assumed contract between author and reader where reality is to be understood according to certain paradigms.” (pdf) Who's the one that making contract in the game's case?</p>
<p>“Following Jesper Juul’s discussion in Half-Real: Videogames between Real Rules and Fictional Worlds: “Rules separate the game from the rest of the world by carving out an area where the rules apply; fiction projects a world different from the real world” (2005, p. 164).” (pdf)</p>
<p>“In video games, the rules are initially hidden from the player—this means the player is more likely to use the game world to make inferences about the rules. In fact, the player may need a fictional game world to understand the rules.” (pdf) Also from (Juul 2005). Game as the intermediate b/w rules and player, instead of rules b/w game and player. But how about tabletop games, are they the same?<br>
Gameplay Conventions</p>
<p>“video games have remediated conventions from theater and film.” (pdf) notice the relation of games, theater and film</p>
<p>“The first type of gameplay convention—briefly discussed above—consists of the ones giving the gamer support or information so that s/he can play the game more easily.” (pdf)</p>
<p>“The second general type of conventions is composed of the ones that hinder the gamer’s progression and success.” (pdf) in other words, challenge<br>
Genre Conventions</p>
<p>“conventions do move from one genre to another so as to widen or renew the experience of a genre.” (pdf)<br>
Narrative and Ohter Conventions at Play</p>
<p>“Indeed, not all video games tell stories. But when they do, mostly in the course of the campaign or journey of single-player games, they rely on a prevalent method, that is, on a “typical oscillation between [cut-scenes] and play.”” (pdf)</p>
<p>“The conflict revolves around the good vs. evil paradigm. No matter the various/numerous forces involved or the sinuous road taken and, above all, regardless of the number of failures (or “game overs”) the gamer experiences or how long it takes him/her to progress, the player-character always succeeds (or always ends in defeat in arcade games, where it is a question of how long the gamer can last).”</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[甘泽谣]]></title>
        <id>https://donkeypoid.github.io/post/gan-ze-yao/</id>
        <link href="https://donkeypoid.github.io/post/gan-ze-yao/">
        </link>
        <updated>2024-06-24T16:22:50.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li>唐朝袁郊撰写的传奇小说集，共一卷。</li>
<li>袁郊：袁郊，字子乾（一作之仪），蔡州朗山（今河南确山北）人。生卒年不详。唐懿宗咸通间曾官祠部郎中，又为虢州刺史。</li>
<li>成於咸通九年**(868)**。《郡斋读书志》著录《甘泽谣》“载谲异事九章”，今存八篇，疑所缺的一篇，即袁郊的“自序”。</li>
<li>事迹包括：粪火煨芋（李泌）、 滚石驱虎</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 id="懒残篇">懒残篇</h2>
<p>懒残者，名明攢。天宝初衡岳寺执役僧也。退食既收所余而食，性懒而食残，故号懒残也。昼专- - 寺之功，夜止群牛之下，曾无倦色，已二十年矣。<br>
时，邺侯李泌 [^1]，寺中读书，察懒残所为，日“非凡物也”。听其中宵梵呗，响彻山林。李公情颇知音，能辨休戚，谓“懒残经音，先凄惋而后喜悅，必谪堕之人，时将去矣。”候中夜，李公潜往谒焉。望席门通名而拜，懒残大詢，仰空而唾曰“ 是将贼我”。李公愈加敬谨，惟拜而已。懒残正拨牛粪火，出芋啖之。良久乃曰“可以席地”。取所啖芋之半，以授焉。李公奉承就食而谢。谓李公曰“慎勿多言，领取十年宰相。”又拜而退居。<br>
一月，刺史祭岳，修道甚严，忽中夜风雷而一峰頹下其緣，山磴道为大石所栏，乃以十牛縻绊以挽之。又以数百人鼓噪以推之，物力竭而石愈固，更无他途可以修事。懒残曰“不假人力，我试去之。”众皆大笑，以为狂人。懒残曰“何必见嗤，试可乃已。”寺僧笑而许之。遂履石而动，忽转盘<br>
而下，声若震雷。山石既开，寺僧皆罗拜，一郡皆噓至圣，刺史奉之如神。懒残悄然，乃怀去意。<br>
寺外虎豺忽尔成群，日有杀伤，无繇禁止。懒残曰“授我等，为尔尽驱除之。”众皆日“大石犹可推，虎豹当易制。”遂与之荆挺。皆蹑而观<br>
之，才出门，见一虎赚之而去。懒残既去，虎亦绝踪。后李公果十年为相也。</p>
<hr>
<p>[1]: 722-789, 中唐名相。</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
</feed>